A Guide to the Virginia Dept. of Rail and Public Transportation, Eastern Shore Railroad Records, 1987-2007
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Dept. of Rail and Public Transportation, Eastern Shore Railroad Records, 1987-2007
The Library of Virginia
44252
3 cu. ft.
Virginia Dept. of Rail and Public Transportation
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred by Marie Berry, Rail Division, Virginia Dept. of Rail and Public Transportation, Richmond, Virginia, 13 April 2009.
Historical Information
The Virginia Dept. of Rail and Public Transportation (DRPT) was initially a section of the Virginia Dept. of Transportation. In 1992, the DRPT was established as a separate agency responsible for rail and public transportation services. The Department reports to the Secretary of Transportation, but also continues to work closely with the Dept. of Transportation. The DRPT focuses on the movement of people and goods throughout the Commonwealth by concentrating on railroads, public transportation and commuter services. The mission of the DRPT is to improve the mobility of people and goods while expanding transportation choices in Virginia.
The Dept. of Rail and Public Transportation supports passenger and freight rail initiatives through advocacy, funding, providing advice, and conducting research. To safeguard Virginia's interests in the national rail network, the Department also represents the Commonwealth's interests regarding national rail issues. The Department also partners with, advises, supports and funds public transportation programs statewide, such as bus systems and commuter service organizations.
The Eastern Shore Railroad was a short-line railroad that began operations in 1981 on the New York, Philadelphia and Norfolk rail line that connected Pocomoke City, Maryland, to Cape Charles, Virginia. To traverse the remainder of the route, the railroad utilized a rail ferry service to move cars across the Chesapeake bay between Cape Charles and Norfolk, Virginia. The Eastern Shore Railroad interchanged with the Norfolk Southern Railway at both Norfolk and Pocomoke City. The Eastern Shore Railroad was bought by the Bay Coast Railroad company in 2006 and now operates under that name.
Scope and Content
Contains a variety of records relating to the Virginia Department of Rail and Public Transportation and its involvment with the Eastern Shore Railroad. Most of the files are related to grants and funding for track rehabilitation and planning projects. Also included are budget records, quarterly reports, audit documents, and agreements.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Records, 1987-2007
Contents List
- Records, 1987-2007.
  - Box 1 (003-109).
    - DRPT Audits, 1988-1989.
    - ANTDC Ledger Sheets, 1989-1997.
    - ES Quarterly Reports, 1988-1994.
    - R-ES Audits, 1990-1997.
    - Quarterly Performance Reports, 1991-1997.
    - Abandonments, 1987-1994.
    - LRFA Financial Status Reports, 1991-1997.
  - Box 2 (003-110).
    - H and B Railroad Rehabilitation Contract, MP 52.5-MP 93, 1992-1993.
    - ESHR Rehabilitation Project, MP 52.5-MP 93, Rebid, LRFA-VA-91(1), 1992-1993.
    - Contingent Interest Agreement / Agreement for LRFA Section 5 DOT Act, 91(1), 1991-1993.
    - Grant Agreement, LRFA-VA-91(1), Rehabilitation, 1991-1992.
    - Funding Application, LRSA-VA-91(1), Rehabilitation, 1990-1991.
    - Grant Agreement, LRFA-VA-91, Planning, 1991.
    - Funding Application, LRSA-VA-91, Planning, 1990-1991.
    - Audit Expansion II, LRSA-VA-90(1), Supplemental Agreement, 1990-1993.
    - Grant Agreement, LRSA-VA-90(1), Rehabilitation / Delaware Funds, 1990.
    - Grant Agreement, LRSA-VA-90, Planning, 1990.
    - Funding Application, LRSR FY90, Rehabilitation, 1990.
    - Funding Application, LRSA-VA-89, Planning, 1988-1989.
    - Grant Agreement, LRSA-VA-85, 1992.
    - Budget Revisions, LRSA-VA-84(1), LRSA-VA-84(2), LRSA-VA-85(2), 1989.
  - Box 3 (003-111).
    - De-obligated Fund Balances, FRA, 1993.
    - FRA Grant Reconciliation, 1992-1995.
    - OIG-DOT Audit, FRA Funds, 1991.
    - Consultant Agreement Audit, FRA Grants Prior to 1981, ANTDC, 1994.
    - Supplemental Audit Agreement, ESHR, 1990-1991.
    - Audit Expansion Agreement, 1990.
    - Grant Close-Outs, PR-VA-80, LRSA-VA-90 and 91, LRFA-VA-93, 1997-2007.
    - Grant Close-Outs, LRSA-VA-82 through LRSA-VA-88(1), 1993.
    - Grant Agreement, DTFR53-02-G-00018, 2002.
    - Grant Agreement, LRFA-VA-94(1), Shenandoah Valley Railroad, 1994.
    - Funding Application, LRFA-VA-94(1), Shenadoah Valley Railroad Rehabilitation, 1993-1994.
    - Agreement, LRFA-VA-94, 1994.
    - Funding Application, LRFA-VA-93(1), Staunton, Disc. and Deob., 1993-1994.
    - Funding Application, LRFA-VA-93(1), Rehabilitation, 1993.
    - Grant Agreement, LRFA-VA-93, Planning, 1992-1993.
    - Planning Application, LRFA-VA-93, Planning, 1992.
    - Grant Agreement, LRFA-VA-92, Planning, 1992.
    - Funding Application, LRFA-VA-92, Planning, 1991.
    - Rehabilitation Agreement, ANTDC, CVRR, VDRPT, 91(1) and 92, 1997.